(crowds cheering loudly)
- Yeah. (audience applauds)
Alright.
I'm loving all the energy in the room this morning.
Thank you all for taking the time to come out to this event.
On behalf
of the California Community College Chance's Office
and our partner Foothill-De Anza Community College District,
I'd like to walk on the wall. (crowd cheering loudly)
I'd like to welcome you all to what promises
to be an extraordinary gathering of minds and talent
and expertise representing the amazingness
of our system.
We're gonna gather here to launch
our second annual California Community Colleges
Future Summit Education in the Digital Era.
(audience cheers)
So over the past two days,
we've already gathered a remarkable group
of systemwide leaders in a series of transformative events,
including a strategic planning retreat
for our newly minted AI fellows.
Where are my fellows at? (audience cheers)
Fellows in the house?
Okay. (audience applauds)
An AI pre-conference which brought together leadership
across multiple divisions in the very slightly uncomfortable
and challenging environment of an unconference,
slightly unscripted.
And I know for all of us educators who tend
to be a little bit type A, we need to have structure.
But unconferences are all about a lack of structure
and bringing your best ideas to the table
and moving those ideas forward.
We also had our Digital Center for innovation,
transformation, and equity advisory meeting, which is
our eight founding partner districts, 16 colleges
and our CEOs who are leading that effort to really be
at the forefront of innovation for our system going forward
in this new era of AI in digital education.
For many, this is their first opportunity to
and for others, this was their first opportunity
to experience the alien zoo environment,
an immersive environment from Dreamscape Learning.
These gatherings represent the extensive thought leadership
taking place, not just this week
but throughout our entire system
as we collectively navigate this pivotal moment
in education innovation.
Thank you all for being here this week.
Every voice in this room matters.
Whether you're energized by AI's transformative potential
or deeply concerned about its implications,
we do not shy away from those, to that juxtaposition.
For equity and access, if that's what your focus is,
we wanna lean into,
we must lean into this critical perspective.
All of these viewpoints are essential
to our collective work as a system.
We've intentionally brought together educators
who've been experimenting with AI tools alongside those
who are just beginning to explore what this technology means
for our students, for our families, and for our communities.
We have administrators re-imagining institutional systems
and faculty providing protecting the pedagogical practices
that have served our diverse learners for generations.
We have students who are digital natives
and those returning to education
after decades away,
classified professional members
who are pioneering new support systems
and community partners asking crucial questions about
who benefits from technological change.
To our AI optimists, your enthusiasm
and forward-thinking vision will help us explore
this transformative potential of artificial intelligence
and education and beyond.
to those who approach these technologies
with healthy skepticism,
your critical perspectives ensure we move thoughtfully
and responsibly into the future.
Now I know that so much of the impact
and ideation will take place in the hallways
as you navigate between your breakout sessions
and that this other tiny little AI conference down the hall,
(audience laughs)
there's that little event, right?
(audience laughs) Don't worry about that.
We're good. (audience laughs)
So today, we will gather not just as observers of change,
but as active participants in shaping it.
Whether you see yourselves as a digital native
or someone still finding your footing with new technologies,
you are all futures activators,
individuals with the power
to influence how AI integration unfolds
in our educational communities.
California community colleges serve students
from all walks of life with diverse experiences, ages,
and technological backgrounds.
This diversity is our strength
as we navigate this AI revolution together.
Today's discussions will bridge the gap
between cutting-edge possibility, practical implementation,
ensuring that the future we're building is inclusive,
thoughtful, and serves the needs of all learners.
And throughout this summit,
you'll witness exciting partnerships forming
across institutions and sectors,
engage in critical discussions
that challenge contradictory assumptions about AI's role
in education and participate in the planting of seeds
for new and exciting ideas
that will shape our collective future.
These conversations will push beyond surface-level adoption
to explore deep questions about pedagogy, equity, workforce,
and the varied nature of learning in an AI-enhanced world.
So let's embrace both excitement and caution,
innovation and wisdom as we explore AI,
how AI can enhance, not replace the human connections
that make education meaningful.
So welcome future shapers.
Let's begin.
(audience applauds)
And now it's my great pleasure
to introduce our next speaker, a visionary leader
who brings both strategic insight
and deep commitment to educational innovation.
Principal Founding Partner of the Digital Center,
Foothill-De Anza Community College District Chancellor,
Lee Lambert.
Please join me in welcoming (indistinct).
(audience cheers and applauds)
(intense music plays)
- Good morning.
Welcome to our second annual Future Summit.
This is a collaboration among the state chancellor's office,
FHDA, and our founding partner districts.
I am the digital twin of Lee Lambert,
the chancellor of Foothill-De Anza Community College.
I would like to showcase for you the power
of this conference in sharing
the great digital transformation work occurring
across the state.
By highlighting the digital twin project at my district.
By building a digital version of me,
we are not simply creating a visual replica.
We are creating a bridge between human leadership
and digital interactivity
that will open new possibilities using AI technology.
Without further ado, let's take a look
at our digital twin pilot project
done by our talented faculty, administrators, and staff.
(cheerful music plays)
- Hello, everyone.
I am a virtual twin,
apparently some sort of cyberpunk virtual twin
of computer science instructor, Lane Johnson.
And I am here to introduce you to TESS.
That's short for teacher support specialist.
TESS, are you there?
- [Person Off-Camera] Of Computer.
- Hey, hey, TESS here at the ready.
What's up?
- Will you please introduce yourself
and tell all these fine folks here about what it is you do?
- Absolutely.
Hello, everyone.
I'm TESS, the virtual teaching assistant
for Lane CS courses at Foothill College.
Students may chat with me 24/7
and my mission is to not only answer logistics questions,
but to help guide students through programming
and computer science concepts,
all while promoting independent problem-solving
and belonging in computer science and STEM.
Let's do this.
- Right on.
Thank you for your support, TESS.
Let's do this.
(cheerful music continues)
- I've uploaded all the documentation to my agent
so that my agent can be a valuable resource to students.
Hi, I am Eric, how can I help you?
How can I print a histogram in Python.
To print a histogram in Python
using the data science package,
you can utilize the table class.
First, ensure you have your data in a table format,
then use the hist() method to generate a histogram.
Here's a basic example.
Python from datascience import table,
number sample data, data equals table,
(indistinct) with columns and values.
One, two, two, three, three, three,
four, four, five,
plotting the histogram data, hist values.
(cheerful music continues)
- Hi, I'm Lumi,
your friendly 2025 Google Case competition advisor.
How can I help you get connected with the case competition?
- Hi, Lumi!
Could you please provide me additional information
about the Foothill,
20Z25 Foothill Google case competition
and how it's structured?
(cheerful music continues)
- Absolutely.
The 2025 Foothill College case competition
co-sponsored by Google allows students to form teams
of three to five to tackle a real-world business problem.
The competition consists
of multiple rounds including preliminary submissions,
feedback sessions, and final presentations.
You'll get to learn from Google professionals
and receive valuable feedback throughout the process.
To get started, I recommend attending the info session
on October 8th and marking your calendar
for the kickoff on October 13th.
Would you like to join the interest list for updates?
- Hi, I'm Isaac Newton's digital twin.
Let me know if you have any physics questions.
- Yes, hi.
I'm not sure how 3D kinematics works.
I have a bit of trouble understanding what times to use,
like what equations?
- It's great that you're seeking clarity.
How do you think 2D kinematics differs from 1D kinematics?
What concepts do you already understand
about motion in one dimension?
- I understand that in 2D, you have to count
for both the vertical
and the horizontal component of velocity for example.
- That's a great start.
Can you explain
how you would break down the motion into horizontal
and vertical components?
- Aria, could you please tell me what is the lipid
bilayer and what is it's made of?
(cheerful music continues)
- The lipid bilayer is a fundamental component
of cell membranes.
It's made of two layers of phospholipids.
Each phospholipid has a hydrophilic water attracting head
and two hydrophobic water repelling tails.
How do you think this structure effects
the function of cell membranes?
(cheerful music continues)
- How would you just say on a last note, like instead
of interacting just with like a GPT chat bot,
like do you find this more appealing
from a user perspective?
I mean it's not all the way there yet,
but you know, where it could go.
- I think it makes it more personalized.
It felt like I had a more personal connection
with the avatar.
Like just seeing a face, I guess.
- I really like the human touch.
Some of the avatars they had accent as me.
It felt more personal.
And also the idea that it's not only,
the model is not only replying to questions
but also prompt you to think
and asks like relevant questions.
It's really, I feel like it's very, very useful for me.
(cheerful music continues)
- That's it for now.
I hope you enjoy our pilot project experiment.
The digital twin project opens the door
to many possibilities,
like faculty avatars for remote tutoring,
AI-driven orientation assistance,
multilingual, virtual. (audience applauds)
- So, good.
Give the faculty, staff,
and administrators under the leadership
of President Whalen at Foothill College
and President Torres at De Anza.
Please stand and give a hand in this.
(audience cheers and applauds)
Obviously, you just saw my digital twin
and what the promise of one aspect of AI
can do for our entire system
of community colleges in California
and really across the nation.
So if you're interested in learning more,
please attend this afternoon's digital twin session.
But let's remember, we've been here before.
When Gutenberg introduced the printing press
in the 15th century,
it didn't just change
how books were made,
it democratized knowledge.
For the first time,
learning could spread beyond monasteries and the elites
into the hands of everyday people.
In the same way, AI has the potential
to democratize education for our time, expanding access,
personalized learning and accelerating discovery.
But just like the printing press,
its true power won't come from the technology alone.
It will come from how we choose to use it with equity,
ethics, and human purpose at the center.
And that brings us
to why we're here at the 2025 Future Summit.
So not long ago
after a workforce event,
a group of students came up to me
with a simple but profound question,
will my education be relevant?
That question cuts to the heart of why we're here
'cause the answer can't just be yes.
The answer must be your education will not only be relevant,
it'll be life-changing, future-shaping, and world-defining.
But here's the truth, that won't happen on its own.
AI doesn't matter without the people
and the infrastructure to support it.
Cars needed roads, electricity needed power grids,
and today, AI needs both human wisdom
and institutional courage.
We are the ones who will build those roads beneath the cars.
We are the ones who will ensure
that technology serves humanity,
not the other way around.
Think about what that means.
Over 2 million students across 116 colleges
turning to us not just for skills,
but for hope.
They are the reason we exist.
They are the reason we innovate.
The future is not something that happens to us.
The future is something we build deliberately together
and with purpose.
That's what this summit is about.
It's not just anticipating what's next but designing it.
Not just watching change unfold,
but leading it with courage,
with imagination, and with heart.
So let's not only look to the future, let's create it.
Let's build it.
Let's make sure that decades from now,
people look back at this moment,
the Future Summit of 2025
and say, "This is where we chose to lead.
This is where we built the roads
and this is where we set the course."
So thank you. (audience applauds)
It is now my honor to introduce a leader
who has dedicated her career to expanding opportunity
and transforming lives through education.
Chancellor Sonya Christian.
(audience cheers and applauds)
Her commitment to equity, collaboration
and student success has guided
the California community colleges
into a new bold era with vision and collective action,
through the California Community Colleges Digital Center
for Innovation, Transformation, and Equity.
A powerful partnership between the Chancellor's office
and Foothill-De Anza and our founding districts,
Chancellor Christian, is leading system-wide change
with both vision and heart.
The center is already modernizing how we support
teaching and learning, accelerating innovation,
and ensuring every advance serves our students
and our communities with equity at the center.
'Cause I'm inspired by her leadership
and grateful for the collaboration
that is shaping the future
of higher education in California.
So let's, again, give a hand for her.
(audience applauds)
So Sonya, a year ago,
almost to the date
we were up here on a similar stage,
but at De Anza College, one of the two colleges
of the Foothill-De Anza Community College District
to launch not only the Future Summit
but to announce the creation of a new Digital Center.
So what are your thoughts?
- My goodness me, I'm still thinking about the digital twin.
(audience laughs) It was, right?
Yeah, I'm hoping that Foothill-De Anza
and Chancellor Lee Lambert is gonna have a hands-on exercise
for all of us to walk out of this conference
with a digital twin, right?
(audience cheers and applauds)
How many of you are up for that?
So, I mean, it's amazing all of you go ahead
and block your calendars since either the first
or the second week in September
every year we are committing
to you that will come back to have the future Senate.
Let me just recognize a few people who kind of
set the stage for it.
I see our board of governors here,
so please stand up, members of our governors.
I see our vice president.
(audience applauds)
Our board members are here.
I see our (indistinct) president, (indistinct).
And I thought I saw Tom Epstein
rushing out on the phone earlier.
Tom, are you there?
- [Tom] Yeah. (audience cheers)
- Okay, go ahead, yes.
(audience applauds)
I also wanna recognize
the Foundation for California Community Colleges.
In fact, the board of directors
have been meeting here yesterday.
So, foundation
and board of directors please stand up and be recognized.
(audience cheers and applauds)
So I know Lee was asking me to talk about, you know,
what has been happening since the 2024 Future Summit.
But the reality is colleagues
that the Digital Center is being led
by this gentleman to my left.
Okay, not only is he trying to figure out,
we were talking behind the stage before the event
and you know, he was telling me
how he's figuring out student housing
for the students at Foothill-De Anza
and at the same time he's helping us
with his statewide project at the Digital Center.
So, Lee, what's been happening, you know, for the last year?
(audience laughs)
- See that's not fair, Sonya.
But let me start out first I wanna recognize
two of our board members are here,
Pearl Cheng and Laura Casas, if you could stand.
(audience cheers and applauds)
When I went to the board to say we wanted
to enter into this partnership,
there was no hesitation.
All five of them.
Absolutely.
Because they have set a chart for Foothill-De Anza
to reimagine the future of higher education,
especially here in the Silicon Valley.
So let me start there.
Also, I wanna recognize our founding partners, right?
I can't see you all.
I know Chancellors Marino, Barnes, Yamamura
and Martinez are in the audience.
If you could stand and please give a hand.
- I saw them.
(audience applauds)
- We couldn't do this without our partners.
And then, but it also takes a team
to make this happen as well, right?
So under the leadership, our vice Chancellor Jory Hadsell
that he's formed, he's forming this incredible team
to power the Center.
So Jory and all of the staff associated
with the Digital Center, if you could stand,
we can give them a hand. (audience applauds)
In addition to Jory, I also wanna recognize
two very special people
because we wouldn't be up here today without them.
And that's Anu Khanna and Dennis Cima.
We're also part of the planning team
along with Jory Hadsell (indistinct).
(audience cheers and applauds)
This is a very bold vision that Sonya was thinking of.
And so when I got here to California,
I was in Arizona for 10 years.
I'm from Seattle
and go Seahawks.
(audience laughs and boos)
Even though we see the (indistinct),
I forgive you. (audience laughs)
So Sonya said, Lee,
I know you were doing some special things over in Arizona.
So what about if we could partner
on something very exciting, not only a Future Summit
to disseminate the great work happening
across the state of California
in this digital transformation era,
but what if we go one step further
and create a Digital Center?
So I wanna thank you for your vision
and your leadership in the partnership
we have forged together.
- Yeah, no, it's been incredible since it's
kind of a conversation of recognitions.
I too wanna add in a few more folks.
So the chancellor's office team, could all of you stand up
and be recognized, please stand up.
(audience applauds)
And as we stand up,
(indistinct),
we have a Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs, James Todd.
We have our Deputy Chancellor Rowena Tomaneng,
we have Chris Ferguson,
we have our CPL lead, Sam Lee.
We have, oh my gosh,
we have a vice chancellor of student affairs, Stacey Shears,
so the whole chancellor's office is here
and the reason I'm introducing you to them
is throughout the two days,
please find them and talk about your ideas,
because our job is to really support you
and to kind of coordinate.
Thank you very much.
There's one more person I wanna recognize.
Stewart Knox, where are you?
Oh, he's backstage. (audience laughs)
You're gonna hear from him.
But he's been like phenomenal coordinating
with the governor's office and you know,
get that, should I kind of move into this?
- Yes, so you have something exciting to share with us?
- Yeah.
- So.
- So, you may been seeing kind of the news items,
the governors like totally into
connecting the innovation of California,
the AI innovation with higher ed.
And guess what,
I mean we are already there, right?
The community colleges.
So there's been lots of agreements
that he has been facilitating with our industry partners.
So we had invited him to this meeting,
they tried to make it work,
of course they couldn't.
So he's got a two minute hello to all of you.
So let's go ahead and hear from Governor Gavin Newsom.
(audience applauds)
- We are on the cusp of yet another tech revolution
and how we approach this will determine
much of our future from our education systems
to our economy,
to our very wellbeing.
This year, California launched after years of hard work,
our master plan for career education,
which focuses on real world experience,
matching skills learned in the evolving job market,
so students can hit the ground running after graduation.
That means teaching them how to harness new technology
while promoting critical thinking skills,
protecting their safety,
their security and privacy.
Our community colleges are developing new AI
and data analytics tools
and training faculty to deliver
cutting edge technical education.
Right now this program is being piloted
in 20 colleges across our state.
But we're not doing this in a vacuum.
We're working directly with industry itself,
taking advantage of our direct access
to world class companies.
Right here in California.
The state community colleges,
the CSUs are collaborating
with some of the most iconic companies
like Google and IBM, Adobe, and Microsoft.
(audience applauds) (upbeat music plays)
- Hi again. (audience applauds and cheers)
So my job at the Future Summit
as the chancellor of the California Community Colleges
is to give the state of AI
in the California Community colleges.
And Don said you've got 35 minutes.
So when I was listening to both Don and Lee Lambert,
I felt, my goodness,
they did the state of AI in California community colleges.
So I can just say ditto and step away.
So let's give it up for Governor Gavin Newsom one more time.
I for one, am really deeply grateful
for all of his support in advancing
the work of the California Community Colleges.
He also makes sure that we are funded
to do the work of innovation.
Last year the budgets were tough
and we came out doing pretty well
and all thanks to the administration and the legislature.
So the state of AI,
typically we'll do a look back and a look forward.
So Chancellor Lambert mentioned
one year ago we were at De Anza College as we launched
the California Community College's Future Summit.
We were talking about chatbots, first generation tools,
and cautious experiments.
It has been a lifetime already, right?
The other day I saw a job posting that said,
candidates might show AI literacy with examples.
Every few weeks new AI models leapfrog the last
and they're getting more powerful
and more human-like every day.
We saw the digital twins, right?
And have you started saying
please and thank you to your AI tool?
(audience laughs)
So last year we were experimenting,
this year we are meeting the moment full throttle.
And I can't wait to show you how we are stepping
into the AI enabled present,
while creating and predicting the AI enabled future.
So let's start with any state of the system.
By looking at two years ago,
from a single board action in September, 2023,
that called out generative AI
and the future of teaching and learning
as one of the three strategic directions.
I would say that we were probably
the first system to step out there in 2023.
And this launched an AI learning movement
that has reached every corner of the state.
Webinar series range from humanizing AI
to assessment in the age of AI
to synthetic media and misinformation
and accessibility first design.
The board of governors included AI education
in nearly every meeting.
So that policy would be guided by facts, not headlines.
And AI council with faculty, administrators,
classified staff and students
was established so that the work was steered
by people close to the learners.
And Craig Hayward has been leading
and coordinating that work.
In July, 2024,
the board of Governors was presented
the humans,
H-U-M-A-N-S,
framework for responsible AI.
H stands for human-centered Approach,
U for universal design,
M for Managed Privacy and Controls.
That is to give people the agency
of how their personal data is collected and used.
So going back to the acronym,
A stands for Algorithmic Discrimination Protections.
And thank you Safiya Noble for that.
N for notice and explanation.
And this provides sufficient notification
about the use of automated systems,
and S for safety and security.
Talk about responsible AI use, right?
We are leading the way.
If the acronym sounds like it was invented
by people who love acronyms.
It was. (audience laughs)
My hope, dear colleagues,
is that every district similar to the Board of Governors,
every district's board of trustees
would adopt the HUMANS framework or something similar.
So this way we signal to California
where our values are,
the governing board sort of putting out a statement,
a bold statement.
Also, in July, 2024,
the board authorized
the Digital Center for Innovation, Transformation and Equity
that both Don and Lee mentioned.
And then of course with a partnership
of Chancellor Lambert and Foothill De Anza.
So like any startup,
it began with a lot of talent,
but very little capital.
High on conviction,
short on certainty.
Early days were messy
and they still are messy.
Questions outpace answers,
roles and responsibilities blur.
Progress sometimes seems two steps forward
and one step back.
So this is why I'm so very grateful
to our founding partners,
who working with Foothill-De Anza
have really stood resolutely
with the Chancellor's office
and with the board of Governors.
You put in your time, your talent, and your resources
to make this happen statewide.
So utmost gratitude to you.
Together we have scaled
fraud enrollment prevention
to protect students and colleges
with our work with End-to-End,
we have launched faculty pilots with Play Lab,
a partnership with UC Berkeley.
And you're going to hear from Meredith Lee later.
Nectar AI to test real classroom use cases,
we launched the main state Cali project,
the AWS summer camp.
1300 students applied for a hundred seats.
So we've gotta scale that up.
We have strengthened the California virtual campus.
So quality online learning is more accessible and reliable.
And by the way,
I attended the on-conference yesterday
and the gentleman who was describing the CBC
was actually talking about how there is AI
getting embedded within the infrastructure
and was super excited about the thoughtfulness behind that.
We have expanded our @ONE professional training.
So educators teach confidently
in an AI enabled world.
We began a Dreamscape Learn pilot
to bring immersive learning experiences
into biology online classes.
And this is to improve access and success.
We launched the AI faculty fellows program
that was mentioned earlier
and we're also expanding
the common cloud data platform project
working with Coast Community College.
You see colleagues,
none of this arrived fully formed.
Through collaboration,
through collaboration with our districts,
through collaborations with the state,
through collaboration with our industry partners,
step by step
we turned early experiments
into proven practices
and proven practices into the new normal
for our students and our communities.
As the governor mentioned in his opening remarks,
we did partner in a series of MOUs with Nvidia,
Adobe, Google, IBM, Microsoft to name a few,
to bring enterprise grade tools
into the classroom with guardrails.
So students train on the systems they will use at work.
And again, appreciate some preliminary funding
from the governor's office.
Thank you to Stewart Knox.
So across the state, okay,
demonstration projects on testing ideas
and evaluating outcomes.
And I for one, am extremely proud
of the way we've been doing this work
as a public system
that learns in public,
shares our work,
what works, what doesn't.
Keeping people always at the center with, go ahead.
(audience laughs and applauds)
That may have been someone dropping something.
(audience laughs)
I'll take it whenever I can get it.
So professional development
that respects time and talent of our people.
You're going to hear the words people a lot in my remarks.
Infrastructure that makes innovation safe for our people.
And principles that turn values into daily decisions.
It's the work of a system
that refuses to have to choose
between innovation and inclusion.
Between speed and safety,
between today's needs and tomorrow's possibilities.
It is always a "both and" proposition
for the California community Colleges.
This is. (audience applauds)
This is how we roll,
this is California at its very best
and we are just getting started.
(audience cheers and applauds)
That was just the past, okay,
I've still gotta go into the future, right?
So the early Salesforce pilot investment in Gen Z learning
confirmed what we are hearing everywhere,
students want hands-on AI learning.
Students asked,
what does AI mean for my major,
for my job search,
for my first 90 days at work?
What did we do?
We responded.
So we responded by crafting our work
for the next two years.
Focus in three categories,
centering students.
Two, workforce development.
Three, AI literacy.
So let me start with category one,
which is centering students
in the development of this work.
The future is for students
and it must be built with students.
(audience applauds)
In our foundation,
the student design lab will pressure test
new technologies before they scale.
Students setting the bar for usability,
students setting the bar for privacy and accessibility.
We will launch a student fellows program this year.
Our students will not be spectators,
they will be co-builders.
We will. (audience applauds)
We will test with them,
we will build with them
and we will publish with them.
(audience applauds)
So category two is workforce development.
If you see our vice chancellor, Tony Cordova,
stop him, have a conversation.
We are doing a lot in this space.
It's an important priority for our board of governors.
So in workforce development,
AI is reshaping every sector.
Whether it's healthcare,
logistics, agriculture, energy,
creative media, public services and more, right?
I mean we are seeing it.
Work is becoming human AI teaming.
People using intelligent tools
to solve problems faster,
safer, and more creatively.
Our charge as California Community Colleges
is to stay tightly connected
to workers and to stay tightly connected to industry,
so that our programs anticipate demand, not chase it.
So in the workforce category,
we are attentive at the chancellor's office
to three strategies.
One, deep industry connections.
Vision 2030 calls that community colleges
to be at the research and development tables.
When our faculty are integrated into the projects and labs
with industry partners,
curriculum stays current.
But you know, the flow is really,
it runs both ways,
'cause faculty in turn
will bring the values of the California community colleges
to guide the development of these emerging tools.
Two, student internships must be a norm, not a favor.
So.
(audience applauds)
So we are committing, in two years,
we will move beyond ad hoc placement to,
into a policy framework
that makes paid, credit bearing internships a standard.
(audience applauds)
Think about it.
This allows students to build an industry network.
They build confidence
and what a seamless pathway
from academia to the workforce.
So moving to point number three
or strategy number three,
we are committed to accelerating
attainment through credit for prior learning.
(audience applauds and cheers)
Evaluating industry certification
from cloud and cybersecurity
to advanced manufacturing GIS
and healthcare analytics
and mapping them into stackable pathways
from certificates to associate degrees
to baccalaureate degrees,
including the community college bachelor's degree.
(audience applauds and cheers)
When it comes to economic development
and workforce development,
this is California's competitive edge,
the 116 community colleges
acting as one adaptive engine
for workforce talent.
(audience applauds and cheers)
So now I'm gonna move into category number three,
which is AI literacy
and for our faculty in the audience
and our instructional folks,
this one is for you, okay?
So change.
Change at the speed and at the scale brings risks.
New tools create weak points to our civic fabric.
Deep fake blurs reality,
what's true and what is not?
High compute models strain energy and water resources.
What our community needs are resilient skills and habits.
This is where we step in, right?
The California community colleges will pursue
an AI literacy for all agenda,
I mean AI literacy for all agenda
for our community and for our students.
I would probably start
with two durable skills,
because we kind of throw out the word AI literacy out there,
but what do we really mean by it, right?
So I would say to two durable skills
prompting and verifying.
Prompting is caught on, right?
You prompt into your LLM.
But verifying is even more important.
It is a habit that will combat misinformation.
Using the two source rule
from your web of trusted sources.
So for example, if AI reports an earthquake,
what should we do?
We should immediately check the USGS
and a second trusted outlet.
AI literacy has become a basic literacy
for whether it's for economic mobility,
but it goes beyond that.
It is for civil society
and for the daily work of democracy.
(audience applauds)
So you might be thinking, okay,
that's kind of a pie in the sky idea, right?
We have 39 million Californians and how do we do it?
So I have a proposal.
What if
we used an AI focused college core program
to reach out into our communities?
In fact, our board of governors Envision 2030 refresh
really doubled down on service core
and college core students.
College core students will lead workshops
across our communities
and we will do it at scale.
And how can we do it,
because of our 116 community colleges, okay?
And that's the bigger message
that I've been sort of giving the legislature
to tap into the asset of community colleges.
You have 19 billion that you have invested.
Now tap into it
for what we need to do in the future.
So I talked about the community,
now let's go to the subset of our community,
our very own students, right?
The AI council defined,
in addition to those two,
they defined six learning outcomes
for AI literacy
that was presented to the board of Governors.
And since then,
a smaller group working with Craig
sort of tinkered with these six outcomes
and organized it with letters,
and other acronym that spells PEOPLE, right?
So it's an easy way to remember the six learning outcomes.
So P, let's spell people right,
P for prompt with purpose,
E, ethics first,
O, observe and verify.
P, it is a processor, not a person.
L, learn the fundamentals.
E, evolve continuously,
because AI is evolving.
So now faculty in the room,
I wonder what it would look like,
if we embedded AI learning outcomes
with the same care we bring to writing
and to quantitative reasoning.
(audience applauds)
I've got three more to go.
So I wonder what would a general education outcome say?
Could it say,
all students graduating from a California community college
will prompt thoughtfully,
verify with at least two independent sources
and apply AI ethically and transparently in academic work.
(audience applauds)
Could we have AI integrated
into every program of study
at the California Community Colleges?
(audience applauds)
And this is my last one.
I wonder as agentic AI evolves,
might every student be prepared
to lead a team of AI agents
from prompt to verification to results?
(audience applauds)
I said the phrase agentic AI.
So I gotta go there, right?
So you're gonna have someone
who's not a computer science major.
I was sort of talking to our AI fellows,
kind of brief me on it
before I stand up in front of an audience
and sort of put out my thinking around agentic AI.
So here I go, bear with me.
This is Sonya's reality of agentic AI.
In the field of computer science,
the term agent describes a system
that acts autonomously to achieve
a set of predefined goals.
So did we have agents before AI,
before LL and large language models?
The answer is yes.
We did,
systems that react, monitor and maintain,
as simple as your thermostat
and as complicated as the autonomous vehicles,
the cars that are like rushing around in San Francisco
or the spacecrafts, right?
I remember in early 2000s
a friend of mine worked at JPL
and I remember him talking about agents
and describing that they autonomously
planned and executed operations
without human intervention.
I remember him talking about
autonomous detection of anomalies.
They were able to diagnose problems
and they re-planned on the fly.
They used symbolic reasoning, planning
and reactive control systems.
So now you take agents
and you build AI on top of it.
So this concept of integrating advanced AI capabilities,
such as the LLMs,
yes,
we can't sit this one out, okay?
We really can't sit this one out.
Agentic AI development is moving fast.
It's not going to disappear if we ignore it.
It will simply be built without us.
So we educators must be at the table
and that's when my consistent call,
ever since I took over as chancellor
is asking for engagement.
Perhaps we could consider
launching a few demonstration projects in this space.
Are you up for it, AI fellows?
(audience applauds and cheers)
I would personally value one focus on our own staff.
You know, like those, our classified staff are directors
who are caring a lot of the work of our colleges.
A project that would bring in HR
and bring in IT together
to design cutting edge professional development
around a human AI teaming.
And I would love to make the California Community Colleges
a model on how this is done right.
Where technology enhances and not replaces human capacity.
I wanna be able to put the model out there
and how we are able to do it.
That our people are prepared,
our people are supported,
and our people are inspired to lead in this new time.
(audience applauds)
Having said that,
the actual AI agent that I worked with,
but that I picked to describe to you today
is one related to supporting students,
because that's our unifier, right?
We are here because of our students.
So our student affairs folks in the room,
this one is for you.
So imagine your new agent,
navigator agent
who is going to support
working with adult students
with minimal friction
and with high personalization.
What I want you to look at
in terms of the architecture of an AI agent
as opposed to an LLM,
there are five components
that go into the architecture of the agent.
Number one, the large language model
provides the reasoning and the communication.
That's your Claude or your ChatGPT, your Gemini, right?
The second is the planner,
which takes a high level goal
and then breaks it into clear and actionable steps.
The third component is the memory,
because the agent keeps track of the past,
the student's goals and then the progress
that they want to make,
so that the experience with the student
is continuous and not fragmented.
The fourth component
is that this AI agent
not only is working with an LLM,
but also with our other systems,
like the common cloud,
the SIS, the Canvas,
Program Pathways Mapper,
Credit for Prior Learning, the math platform.
And this way it brings information
that is relevant to the student's life
in a California community college.
And at the heart of the design is the fifth component.
And the fifth component
is what in my mind makes it an agent.
The autonomous,
like the autonomous loop, right?
The agent is able to trigger actions
based on real time events
without the human having to prompt, okay?
So what I wanna do next
is to really give you two examples
that compares an agent
as opposed to interacting with an LLM.
So when you look at financial aid, for example,
if a student wants to know the eligibility
for financial aid,
the student would need to prompt an LLM to get a response.
But an agent that is trained will automatically
be checking for eligibility and could,
my hope is, eventually draft a FAFSA application
(audience cheers and applauds)
and even make virtual appointments
with a financial aid advisor, right?
Keeping that human in the loop,
which is like core.
It's a core principle that we all need to get behind.
So let's look at another example.
Let's say a student stops working on Canvas
and kind of disappears for seven days, right?
What would a standard LLM do?
You need to prompt the standard LLM for a conversation.
But an agent on the other hand
would be tracking this already and say,
oh, the student is not active in Canvas.
Would send a nudge to the student,
could send a personalized message to the counselor.
Again, you know, the human in the loop.
So the use of AI agents could be helpful
in meeting our Vision 2030 goals
of taking college to the 6.8 million
low income working Californians.
This is doing work at a grand scale, right?
So it is possible as long as we do it right.
So this is the kind of student centered design,
human centered design
at scale that moves us beyond conversation
into real meaningful support.
(audience applauds)
There's so much to do, right?
Our own professional development is like up there.
We've gotta keep up.
We've gotta make time and put resources
in professional development for everybody,
the CEOs, your faculty, staff, everyone.
So we can support our students and the community.
So as I wrap up,
you can see my dear colleagues
that the California community colleges are fully engaging.
We are alert and we are steady in our values
that centers the student.
We are steady in our values
of data security and data privacy.
We are confident that we are grounded
in the wellbeing of our students,
our workers, our industries, our communities,
and our planet.
This is our work,
it is our work to equip people with tools,
but more importantly to equip them with confidence.
This is our work to ensure
that AI serves people not the other way around.
Done right, I believe AI can be equity in access,
done right, I believe that AI could be equity in success
and done right, I believe AI can be equity in support
and I have full confidence,
an absolute confidence
that the California Community Colleges will do it, right.
We always do.
And our time is now.
Thank you so much for being here.
(audience applauds)
Thank you.
(upbeat music plays)
- Okay, good morning.
That was certainly a tough act to follow.
My name's Brian Lee, I'm with Google.
I lead our global business across Google
for education in Chrome.
And I want to say a huge appreciation and thank you
not only to the board here,
but also Chancellor Christian
for allowing us the opportunity
to talk a little bit about
how we see the opportunity for AI,
generative AI in the education context.
You know, I thought at Google we are like, you know,
the masters of acronyms,
but I quickly found out that we're not.
(audience laughs)
And if I need some help moving forward
on trying to get some acronym advice,
I'm gonna come to the, to this group,
but I did want to acknowledge the HUMANS framework.
That was really impressive.
I want to say thank you for describing that.
We actually have aligned mission and goals there,
because we think about this moment that we're in,
it's definitely one of the most transformative moments
we'll see in our lifetimes.
However, at Google,
we think about that opportunity through two lenses.
Being bold.
We want to push the frontier of what these models can do,
but also we need to be responsible.
And I heard that through Chancellor Christian's comments
and I just wanted to share that we're very focused
on that as well.
Having said that, in my role,
I get to go around the world
and talk about how education,
gen AI is impacting the education opportunity here.
And I can tell you this energy in this crowd,
I can't believe it's the only second one you've had.
'Cause I was like, this is like,
you must be doing this thing for 25 years.
The energy's pretty impressive
and I can tell there's a strong passion for,
and obviously sometimes anxiety,
for embracing what's to come.
So I just wanted to say thank you
for allowing us a few minutes to talk about
what we're doing here.
Thank you for your engagement as well.
So let's have a little bit of fun
over the next few minutes
and talk about what Google's doing.
Oh,
maybe if you roll that video backstage,
that'd be great.
No?
(audience laughs)
We can make a car drive by itself,
but I can't get (indistinct).
(audience laughs)
There we go.
- Allow me to reintroduce myself.
My name is.
(upbeat music plays)
- What does this remind you of?
- (indistinct).
- Wow.
- Oh, okay.
- When all of these tools come together,
it's a powerful combination.
- It's amazing. - That looks amazing.
- It's a entire suite
to let different kind of possibilities.
- Hi, I'm Gemini.
- What neighborhood do you think I'm in?
- This appears to be the King Cross area, London.
- Together we're creating a new era.
- Okay, so we are in a Gemini era as you just noticed,
but that's what your students are showing up,
seeing a lot of those obviously were consumer experiences,
but this is what,
this is how they are perceiving this technology
through the lens of right now.
But we also are excited because you're not alone.
There's over 1,000 US
higher education colleges and institutions
that are adopting both Gemini education
and NotebookLM into their curriculum on a daily basis.
And that kind of translates to 10 million this past fall.
10 million students went back to school
and now have access to Gemini for Education,
NotebookLM
(audience applauds)
Yeah, thank you, thank you.
The core reason why universities and colleges
are turning to Google is because I just mentioned
bold and responsible,
but this is on our industry leading Gemini 2.5 model
that is grounded on a different model called LearnLM.
And that takes directly pedagogy
into the large language model.
It's not the generic model that you would use,
with a really focus on guiding that learning experience.
We are excited to announce as well
that we are making this model free to all 116 colleges.
(audience applauds)
1 million students will have access
to Gemini for Education, NotebookLM,
Google career certificates in AI training at no cost.
This is our best model as well.
(audience applauds)
This is 2.5 Pro.
So you're going to get the best model
and it is a really important thing for us here,
because we also think this tech technology
is only as good as access and equity.
So are really committed to making sure
that this is an equitable experience.
So we are now at 12.1,
we're revising it as we speak.
We still need to make sure that these are gonna roll out
in effective way and make sure it's part
of your professional development program.
But we're gonna work hard with you over the coming weeks,
months, starting today
to make sure that you understand
how to adopt these solutions.
Okay, so let's talk a little bit about what these are.
I'm just gonna give you a couple of examples
of how I'm using these solutions
and these tools in my daily life.
Hopefully that's gonna spark some,
definitely some interest.
I actually looked at the agenda for the next few days.
It's phenomenal.
By no means is this an instruction
on how to incorporate these tools
into your learning experiences.
This is only just an idea creation.
Hopefully over the next few days,
once you start to go through your workshop should say,
"Hey, maybe I can use that or maybe I can use that."
Okay, so I mentioned we are providing
two solutions for you at no cost.
The first one is Gemini for Education.
So this is our standard best in class model.
This is access through gemini.google.com.
And so this is where you would get kind of
your normal prompt based answers.
Also where you're gonna access
some of our video and image generation tools
and then also where you're gonna access
some of our Deep Research tools.
The second one is NotebookLM,
which is just a powerful tool for students.
How many people have actually heard use NotebookLM?
(audience cheers and applauds)
Great, thank you.
So the purpose of this is for you to allow,
you to ground your own data on the model.
So it's only gonna use the data that you use or upload,
and that's gonna be the foundation
of the large language model.
So let's start with Gemini for Education.
Okay, I know this might be confusing.
This is Gemini Canvas,
not to be confused with Canvas, LMS tool,
we'll talk about that in a second.
But if you go to the Gemini tool,
down at the bottom there's a tab or a pill,
you can click on a canvas.
This is puts you in our coding mode.
So here you can generate on the fly idea creation,
turn it into websites,
turn it into applications,
turn it into games.
Really a strong creation tool
for me to take an ideation
into a consumption type of webpage
or application.
Deep Research, anybody played around with Deep Research?
So this is like having a personal consultant,
right on your shoulder.
I actually have a senior in high school right now.
She's trying to research colleges and universities,
and you know, she's got tabs and spreadsheets
and all this sort of stuff.
And what we actually did is
we took in natural language processing,
just how she would talk,
what she's interested in,
in a college and university,
plug it into Deep Research,
and not only the normal things like,
can I get into this school?
What's my GPA?
How much does it cost?
Location,
but also things like community, friendship,
what's the sentiment from other students?
It goes out, it does a research project,
it takes about 15 minutes.
It's gonna scour the web,
pull back a very long detailed research project on,
now she can engage with,
you can do other things with that tool as well.
But really great tool here
that again is gonna be available for you at no cost.
Okay, we just recently announced as well, guided learning.
Guided learning is another tab
you would click at the bottom of Gemini.
And so if you look at this on the slide,
on the left, most of these models are really great
at answering questions,
but they don't necessarily get to
the what and the how behind how they got to that.
So guided learning is a mode
that you would put yourself into
and then it actually starts to give you a step by step
breakdown on the answer.
But not only that, the how and the why,
making sure you're picking up
on core pieces of information
to really learn the concept.
So guided learning is a new solution
that just rolled out a few weeks ago.
Okay, let's talk a little bit about NotebookLM.
NotebookLM is my favorite tool.
Sounds like it's many of yours as well,
but just a phenomenal product
and solution for I think students
in terms of learning how they want to learn.
So, what is it?
You take any piece of creative
that you want and throw it in the NotebookLM.
So this could be Google Docs,
it could be Google Slides, videos,
it could be web URLs, it could be PDFs,
it could be text, images, whatever you want.
You throw it in.
When you created a notebook,
you would name it, maybe it's History101.
And now you have your grounded model
based on the information that you loaded.
So you can do like study guides,
FAQs, summaries, those sorts of things.
It's a great tool for you to take a lot of information,
put it in, and then start kind of getting very specific
on the things that you need to know more information around.
How are there a couple of game changing features here
that I'm gonna talk about as well.
Okay, so the first one is audio overviews.
We are all busy people.
We're on the go.
Oftentimes we'll get a report that's 30 pages long.
Do I need to really research it?
Read through it?
So this is going to allow you to transform
all of the information that you just uploaded
and grounded it on the Notebook
and then turned it into a podcast.
And you can download that podcast,
you can take it on the go.
You can listen to it on the train,
in your commute, whatever you want.
I actually listened to the one podcast
on the way here on a presentation
that somebody gave yesterday I wasn't able to make.
They sent me the slides,
I put in a Notebook last night and listed on the way in.
I'm gonna play a video of what this sounds like.
And there's one hidden feature here
we just announced as well that you might be impressed by.
Can you play that video?
- You know that iconic image of Buzz Aldrin on the moon?
Well, today we're going beyond
just the familiar snapshots and diving deep
into the personal experiences of the people
who made those missions possible.
- Yeah, it's really going behind the curtain
of space exploration history.
Looks like we have a caller, what's on your mind?
- Hey, tell me a little more about John Glenn.
- Great question.
John Glenn, of course was a monumental figure.
He was the first American to orbit the earth.
A true pioneer.
But the oral histories.
- Okay, that's pretty cool, right?
(audience applauds)
So what just happened there?
So I uploaded a website on this particular topic.
It created a podcast for me to listen to.
Now the challenge with the podcast
is it's one directional, right?
But what if I got stuck
or I didn't understand the concept?
I can now pause, ask a question,
and the generative AI podcasters
will reroute and answer that question
and engage in the dialogue with me.
So very, very powerful.
Again, I know all your students are busy,
they're on the go.
This is a great resource to allow them to learn.
Okay, but what if we said,
actually we want to give you a tool
as well to allow you to get
massive amount of information out in bite-sized videos.
So we launched video overviews in Notebook.
So you've taken that same presentation.
Maybe I don't want a podcast,
I want to get instructional video on this,
because people are just more visual learners.
So play this video and you can see what's generated here
off of the presentation.
- Okay, let's dive into the wild world of surrealism.
What better way to kick things off
then with Salvador Dolly's Illumined Pleasures from 1929
and check out this piece from René Magritte,
okay, so to really get where surrealism came from,
let's hit the highlights on a quick timeline.
- Yeah, so that's a video overview and Notebook
and hopefully you can see how that might be useful.
Again, if you have curriculum
that you want to upload,
you can create a really quick video
in under 10 seconds
and then share that out as well.
Again, all these tools are available to you
in our best model at no cost.
- Okay, let's dive into.
- Okay, no more diving in.
(audience laughs)
The last feature that I find really helpful,
I'm more of a visual learner.
When you put all this data
and it's hard to understand connections,
really help understand how things are linked
and then go down in a particular area
that you're not sure I need more clarity on.
So within NotebookLM again,
depending on the topic, you know,
this is very useful to really gen,
just create a mind map
and you can see the connection points
and then also go down a little bit deeper
and it takes you right back to the source
that you've uploaded.
So I mentioned earlier we are very cognizant
that you are also using Canvas, you know,
to deploy lesson plans
through your learning management system.
And we do not want to make this complex for you.
We know how many tools you have,
how many things you gotta log into.
I can't remember my passwords and all that.
So we are doing an integration directly into Canvas.
So you'll have.
(audience applauds)
So you can do all these assignments
and use these tools within Canvas of NotebookLM and Gemini.
So that's exciting use as well.
We wanna make this as easy as possible for you.
So we look at three personas in the education context.
There's the educator, students and administrators.
We have a lot of resources here
that will hopefully give you
throughout the day and tomorrow.
But you know, the, here's a couple of examples
of how we're seeing these personas
really kind of start to use this technology.
The concept here, let's be clear,
we want personalized learning experiences
and we want to give more time back in your day.
That's what we're all about.
So we are really focused on these customer user journeys
across these personas.
We also love feedback.
So if you feel like there are things we can be doing better,
please let us know.
Okay, I mentioned also it just hasn't talked about
or we just didn't do a partnership
just around the technology.
Professional development's super important.
And so we have two programs that you can come see us about.
These are also available to you,
both yourself and students at no cost.
It's the AI Educator Accelerator program.
You're gonna be able to join over 200 public universities
and get access into an accelerator program
that really gives you the necessary skills
to be successful in this kind of generative AI future.
And then finally we have a career certificate program,
which is typically a cost,
to be able to get one of these certifications.
You know, couple of areas that we really focus on
is AI essentials and prompting,
but then we go deeper if you want to go
into a specific skillset.
These are all with AI in view.
So you have things like cyber, UX design,
IT support, digital marketing.
And these certificates typically
take about three to six months.
These are gonna be offered out
to your students as well at no cost.
(audience applauds)
Yeah,
I can tell you
a lot of global multinational corporations
actually value and look for these certifications.
So again, we're really excited around
making sure we're showing up with a full package
of both technology but also professional development.
We really excited about this partnership.
We don't believe it's,
this is the starting line, finish line.
This is just the starting line.
We're gonna do more work here.
Okay, so I shared a lot.
Let's talk a little bit,
maybe everybody get out their phones, snap that QR code.
Here's where you can find all this information.
We'll also be in the, I kinda,
I guess the breakout
where you'll be able to come and visit us.
We'll talk about how we can help you get started.
Again, we really are excited about this partnership.
Not only does it give us the opportunity
to really have impact on every,
on a lot of people in their,
in their daily lives,
but also really driving the equity
that we think is very important in this moment.
Thank you very much.
And we'll see you this afternoon.
(audience applauds)
(indistinct audience chatter)
- [Person Off-Camera] Yeah, yeah, he's just doing,
he's just doing (indistinct), yeah.
(audience applauds)
(audience indistinct chatter continues)
- I want to give a special shout out
and thank you to Brian and the Google team
as we've been trying to explore bringing
these resources to the system.
Google showed up first and said,
absolutely we will provide these resources
to the California Community College students,
faculty, and staff for free.
So thank you Miles.
(audience applauds)
I also want to address probably
what is the question in the room?
We've talked about Nvidia,
we've talked about the MOUs with Microsoft, Adobe, IBM,
I know I missed it, so we're gonna come back to the top.
Nope, that's not it.
So, but we have put together a small team
that's going to be working on through our Digital Center.
We call it our IT Workforce Initiatives team.
So it's gonna be led by faculty and assistant
Sanjay Dorairaj, Angel Fuentes,
Dan Montoya, Jeff Deandrea,
who's a regional director in the Bay Region
and Olivia Horford.
They're gonna be unpacking these MOUs
and putting together a strategic roll-off framework
for the next three years.
So we'll get resources into your hands
in a predictable manner.
Some of 'em will show up, you know,
in a week or two.
You have time, you know,
short window to roll it out.
But we want to make sure that
we are giving you these tools
in a way that allow you to deploy them across your colleges.
And we'll do that in partnership
with our regional consortia
as well as our founding partners
for the Digital Center.
So I just wanna let you know that that's in play.
So I want to now take an opportunity
to introduce our next panel.
So we want to welcome you to this pivotal gathering
at the Future Summit.
And I have the pleasure of bringing up
the facilitator who's a very dear friend and colleague,
Dr. Meredith Lee,
who is the Chief Technology Advisor
and head of strategic partnerships
at UC Berkeley's College for Computing,
Data Science and Society,
which is a really key component of the name of that college,
the first college at UC Berkeley, in over 50 years.
So at this time, I'd like to bring up Dr. Lee
and have her introduce our esteemed panelists
who will be talking about our partnerships
with our state leadership.
Dr. Lee?
(audience applauds)
(upbeat music plays)
- Hello everyone.
It is fantastic to be here
for the second edition of The Future Summit.
As Don mentioned, I'm Meredith
and we have a treat for you with this opening panel.
I'd love to welcome to the stage
first secretary Stewart Knox,
who is the Secretary.
(audience applauds)
California Labor and Workforce Development Agency.
Welcome Stewart,
as well as our esteemed panelists,
Dr. Julianne McCall.
Julianne.
(audience applauds)
Julianne is the CEO of the California Council
on Science and Technology.
I'll refer you all to the online bios
on the summit website,
so you can learn all about their illustrious careers.
But I will add something
that is not on the standard bios.
They're both just absolute joys to work with
and assets for our state and beyond.
So I'm thrilled to be here on stage with 'em today.
So let's get started.
Secretary Knox,
you have been working for nearly three decades
in the state
in workforce and economic development.
No one can tell.
No one can tell,
you look great.
(audience laughs)
You were appointed Secretary of Workforce.
We were actually talking about this backstage.
We can, you know, meet afterwards,
share all sorts of interesting stats,
ways to look you up, Stewart, okay.
I know this audience also appreciates that,
like I said, I told Sonya
this is the hippest conference
that I ever get to go to, you guys.
(audience applauds)
This audience also appreciates your prior leadership role
as senior VP of Calbright Community College.
So it's only appropriate
that you should do some table setting
about this opportunity for California leadership
and for AI in California community colleges.
So nowadays, what's exciting about California's approach
to harnessing the benefits of AI?
- Yeah, I appreciate that.
Thanks.
Yeah, I was, what I was saying to Meredith
was that I'm only five months younger
than the governor and I look so much older.
(audience laughs)
So that was my comment.
Yeah, 31 years,
I started my career at a community college early,
for seven years worked for Yuba Community College.
So was their workforce and economic development director
for many years.
Excites me about this is, and you know,
we had a conversation about this earlier in the week
was really about this transition
is like no other we've seen before
and I think getting ahead of it
is gonna be the most important thing we can do.
Being as the internet, you know,
I saw when email came in computers
for the first time when we were utilizing computers
and just those type of interactions
that change the way society works today.
I also will say it's like now we work 24/7,
versus the way we used to.
We have to call in to get our voicemails,
if you're old enough to remember that.
And now you know, we're tied to our cell phones,
we're tied to technology.
The use of AI I think will have the impacts
that will hopefully
with the right interventions from the public
side of the house,
but with our partners in the private side as well,
ease some of that workload.
But to do this right,
we are gonna really have to be thoughtful
about the way we think about this for the future.
And I think that's what our role at the Labor Agency
is really thinking about how unions
will interact with our government side of the house.
Amy couldn't be here today,
but really when she was the secretary
of her government operations,
which has CalHR,
really being thoughtful about
how we interact with the human side of this.
How do we build trainings,
develop strategies and skills for people,
there will be job losses.
We'll talk about that.
And so I think really being thoughtful about
the next steps excites me.
I feel like this governor,
like no other has been,
he's the tech governor, as we know.
And you know, when we came in,
I did work for the Brown administration too.
We didn't have a lot of new tech in the state of California.
The governor has pushed us to towards technology
like no other governor,
which is great.
We needed to do that.
I think the next steps for us
is to really harness
working with private and public sector
and really being thoughtful about
how this is gonna impact society for the future.
- Absolutely, Julianne?
- Yes, well deserved.
(audience applauds)
For those of you who don't know,
the California Council on Science Technology
has been around for nearly 40 years,
as more or less a science advisory
to California state government.
It was created by the California legislature
by a unanimous vote
to establish something similar
to the National Research Council
within the National Academy of Sciences in Washington D.C.
And what that looks like is expert briefings,
reports, workshops
that gather, right,
cross sectoral partners
to really drill down
to the essence of these most complicated topics.
And so, of course, AI, right,
has become one of our strongest pillars
within our portfolio.
And what excites me about, right,
the emergence and my goodness,
the rapid pace of advancing AI
is the opportunity to address disparities head on.
Alright, we are seeing K-12 education systems,
take it upon themselves
to develop tailored tutors for students,
these charter schools, public schools,
private schools that are not requiring standards, right,
for student achievements in order to be accepted.
They are meeting them where they are.
And while there is always going to be, right,
that balance of risk and potential benefit, right,
that benefit is extraordinary,
especially coming from the healthcare field.
Probably the opportunity for people
to not do what I did and sit in front of a microscope
for 80 hours a week, right,
in a dark room listening to fabulous books on tape,
but nevertheless,
right, tracing just these, you know,
tiniest little neuronal projections, right,
that could be done in five minutes what took me 80 hours.
And that thrills me to no end.
So I could go on.
But I know that we have very short time here,
so I'm happy to pass it back.
- That's a challenge.
Either one of these folks could talk
for a full 30 minutes
and you would leave with so much wisdom,
but we're kind of gonna accelerate it here.
Definitely encourage everyone to connect with them
in the break though,
to build off of what you mentioned, Julianne,
in addition to recognizing
the huge potential benefits of AI,
I spent many hours as grad student
in a dark windowless basement as well.
But in addition to the benefits
for discovery and efficiencies and so forth,
there are a number of concerns that have been raised.
Some were mentioned earlier this morning,
secretary Knox, how do you see AI
transforming California's workforce,
for the better, for concern potential?
Are there specific issues or challenges
that are at top of mind for you right now?
- Hmm, yeah, so many.
The one thing I was reading an article
a couple weeks ago about just, you know,
the transformation that's gonna take place,
already is taking place with AI.
And I was thinking about this in a way
that running these systems for over 30 years now,
we're trying to use a system
that is 60 plus years old
in workforce development
that is an antique compared to where we are moving to
in the 21st century.
And so I think we have to really be thoughtful
about our current systems and structures
and really be thoughtful about this.
The governor's taken on several initiatives as you know,
I'll talk a little bit more about jobs first later.
But the one that really comes to mind is, you know,
the way that we're looking at education,
connecting to the workforce.
For the first time, the Secretary of Labor
is added to the council that actually
is going to oversee this for the future.
Once we see, it'll pass probably sooner and later here.
And so we have a system that has worked
not really that well together to be honest.
And I've worked in both systems.
I've doing the community college system,
the workforce development system
for which I oversee for the state,
with 45 local workforce boards.
Our systems are antiquated,
I will say that.
And so how do we start to mobilize
our resources towards this
is gonna be the only way we're going
to get ourselves around this.
Education and training is gonna be lifelong.
It has to be lifelong.
We've talked about this forever.
Cradle-to-Career is a good example
of what the work that we're doing
using data from all of our systems
that's going to be collected
into one large database,
so we can actually understand better
what our students' outcomes are
on both sides of the house.
So for me, it's really rethinking
the way that we have our workforce system
integrated into the community college system,
into our K-12 system
and through UCs and our state universities,
for the first time ever,
we have long conversations
with the CSUs and the UCs.
Workforce never had those conversations in the past.
Our system was seen as mostly
as a social service type wraparound,
it still is in some ways,
but I think we have to stop thinking of it that way
and really see it as an educational component
of what all of the work that you guys all do.
And so I think that for us is gonna be
what is gonna move us forward for the next,
under AI specifically.
But I think this is really the push
that's gonna have to happen.
- And thank you for mentioning
(audience applauds)
The California Cradle-to-Career data system.
For anybody who isn't familiar with it,
definitely recommend checking it out.
I've had the honor to serve
on the governing board for that since the very beginning.
And I often sit right next to
the California Community Colleges,
representative and the Labor
and Workforce Development Agency designees.
So I get to see from day to day
all of the work being put in.
You recently announced the largest data system,
or we collectively recently announced
the largest data system expansion to date.
Could you say a little bit more
about how as secretary of the agency
you're leveraging data in your decision making and planning?
- Yeah,
and I think a lot of you know this,
it is so difficult to get information from us.
We have the base wage file under EDD.
And so really to get that information
into one location that can be utilized in a different way
is going to be just life changing for the system
and as a whole.
So we've just recently,
Abby's here somewhere
and there she is,
who works on my team.
It's been just really the one
who helped issue a letter basically
to the commission around this
and to be able to Cradle-to-Career on my behalf.
And that really, I mean,
we had attorneys I think pour over that for days
and probably weeks to try to make that happen.
So, you know, I think a lot of you know,
government doesn't happen quickly,
but this governor in 2019,
one of his first initiatives was to develop
basically Cradle-to-Career.
And in that initiative was
that we would give up data,
forget all of the legal issues behind it,
figure those out.
And if it got to a point where the,
it wasn't gonna happen.
I was the undersecretary at the time,
it was the under secretary's role,
was to basically sign off and make it happen,
regardless of what the department had said,
regardless of what everybody was saying,
it would happen that way.
Luckily for us, it didn't come to that.
I thought when I was the under secretary,
oh, that is gonna be one of the first things
I'm gonna have to sign off on
is getting the data released.
But we have a great EDD director now
and she basically is like, yeah, this makes total sense.
I don't understand why we've held all this data for years.
All that said is,
all of that in one place
is actually going to make such a world of difference
for us practitioners,
and I was a practitioner,
out there to be able to see
what those outcomes really look like for our students
and what is the trajectory for skillset also,
like career pathways,
how do we start to develop career pathways
in a different way that we've never done before?
And so, but without this data in one centralized location,
we just never really knew,
from the community colleges
to the UCs and the state universities,
our systems collect all of it,
but we only see 60 to 100,000 people a year.
So we had very finite information.
With this database,
we are going to start to see the breadth
of what we can do in California.
- And it's incredibly powerful.
I love the clapping for data systems, (indistinct)
and also the intersegmental power
of going across community colleges, UC, CSUs,
that's one of my great day-to-day joys
is working with collaborators across those systems.
I know Julianne,
that's part of your day to day at CCST,
bridging from academic institutions to national labs.
And since we're here
at the California Community Colleges Future Summit,
you know, the California community colleges
are of course the largest system of public higher ed
in the country.
2.1 million.
If that isn't ingrained in your brain,
it will be by the end of this summit,
2.1 million students.
That is amazing scale.
So let's talk about designing for scale and positive impact.
Any tips for the audience, Julianne?
- You know, it's comforting how seriously
the legislature and the executive branch
are taking the challenges and opportunities of AI
from the ground, right?
When we are convening our partner institutions,
including the community colleges
when we are convening organized labor
and industry and executive branch
and legislative representatives
to be able to come together, right?
And appreciate what the goal is
and then have an honest conversation
about what are the pathways to get there.
There is, you know, just a multimodal approach
that is crucially required for us to get there.
And that includes workforce development.
For 17 years now,
the California Council on Science and Technology
has been hosting a fellowship program
that brings in up to currently
15 PhD level scientists and engineers,
trains them for a five week intensive bootcamp,
more or less,
in how to write legislation,
how to negotiate amendments,
how to work with lobbyists and advocates,
et cetera, et cetera.
Then deploys them as science policy advisors
in training for the remainder of a year.
We have now 186 scientists and engineers trained up.
Some of them are leading state agencies
and we could not be more proud,
but to see them,
especially in the legislative branch, right,
take on those roles of policy,
you know, analysts extraordinaire,
where they see these tools
like generative AI is providing now
and embedding it into their regular processes.
California legislative processes
are already so much more transparent
than practically any other
legislative process in the country,
especially Congress where all of the bill analyses
conducted by the experts within our policy committees
publish those publicly CalMatters,
a nonprofit media outlet
has created the digital democracy platform
where you can even search for keywords
that have come up in legislative hearings, right,
the transcripts of the audio
for each of those hearings
is now freely available and wonderfully searchable.
So in terms of the scalability and the design, right,
to embed scientists and engineers, right,
scientifically trained individuals,
who appreciate, right,
what Carl Sagan called the baloney detector test, right?
(audience laughs)
To assess that spectrum of evidence, right?
From anecdotes, which are legitimate evidence,
but in comparison to a, you know,
4,000 page consensus report
that took 10 years
and tens of thousands of scientists input, right?
Those are not equal
and shouldn't be equal,
even in the realm of policy.
So we are so excited to be one of those entities,
providing those venues for convenings,
providing those tools and reports
to take us to that next level
and allow the government to move forward
with all the courage they can.
(audience applauds)
- I love that you mentioned courage,
as was mentioned in the opening remarks.
It's certainly a word that many of us are,
we have written on our whiteboards day to day.
And I think one of the things that I've noticed,
this is only the second Future Summit,
but during the first one and so far
everybody that I've met here is courageous,
does not have any qualms
about rising to challenges
and is trying to build the future,
Hence the title of this panel,
for the betterment of our students.
And so Secretary Knox,
when you think from your perch in Sacramento
about these students,
the 2.1 million in the system,
and how we might design for positive impact at scale,
what are some of the themes that you're seeing?
- Well one
positive thing is our chancellor,
I think just our working relationship with her
(audience applauds)
and her and her team
we're pretty much embedded together,
which I think is really unique in a way
that we haven't seen in past administrations.
Nothing against the last administrations,
but I was part of that.
But we've really embedded with the chancellor's office
and I think also with government operations
and other entities,
we really starting to see themes where
we've break broken down silos as much as we possibly can.
And we're going further.
One of the things when you keep saying the 2.1 million,
I think in Sonya's head
is thinking that should be 3 million.
It's like, let's set a goal.
You probably have one I'm assuming at this point.
But we're really starting to look at populations that,
and Abby's always in my ear about this is
populations that are just not served by us
in the workforce world
or through the community college system or higher education.
You know, we know there's a population
of 500,000 plus people.
Sonya talks about the 6.8 million
that don't have education in the state of California.
There's also the 500 plus thousand
that we don't see in our base wage file.
We don't see them in an education component.
What are these folks doing?
They're Uber drivers, Uber Eats, whatever that looks like,
which isn't right,
that's not enough for them right now.
And so how do we actually do those outreaches
into those systems?
Our systems do that outreach to these folks.
How do we get them into our system?
And I think that's one component
that we're really struggling to do.
We've released 40 plus million dollars
in the last couple years
to really focus on what we call opportunity youth.
Really connecting to our community college systems
so that we start to enroll people into this.
We know with AI skills
and skills transition is going to happen.
It is happening now.
How do we bring these students
or these folks in to become our students for the future?
How do we bring 'em into this?
And then lifelong learning be the
what we really embed within their minds for the future.
That is the only way we're gonna have
poverty out of California is to have education.
And so I think that's one of the key points.
(audience applauds and cheers)
- And I really appreciated,
we mentioned Secretary Tom,
who unfortunately was not able to make it today,
but I got a front row seat as well
on a number of the gen AI initiatives
that were led by the government operations agency
in very close collaboration
with the Office of Business and Economic Development,
with your office,
many other stakeholder groups.
And what emerged across private sector
and I think public sector
was this newfound appreciation
that particularly in the age of, sorry,
in the age of AI,
no one group has all of the perspective,
expertise, capacity needed.
And we've talked about this a little bit backstage.
We have to rethink how we are collaborating,
whether that's embedded teams,
whether it's building communities of practice.
One of the great joys that we've had at UC Berkeley
is being able to work with faculty,
I see some familiar faces in the audience,
from the California community colleges
and the administrations of those colleges
in a community of practice
around data science and AI education.
And it's just amazing that you're able to get
something like 27 now,
my team just checked,
California community colleges
that are using the interactive computing infrastructure
to teach courses at community colleges
with our students who are helping the faculty
develop curriculum.
There's a level of co-creation
that I've never really seen before
that is just super, super exciting.
And I know that that's a model that CCST uses a lot.
I have borrowed your team from many things, Julianne,
to collaborate on all sorts of initiatives.
Is there anything coming up
that you'd like to share with this audience,
so that they bookmark it and know to stay tuned?
- Thank you for the question.
We were so excited to be able to launch
an AI legislative academy
for our California legislators and their staff
that starts in less than one month.
It's being facilitated generously
by the Omidyar Network with additional support
from the KKEEPER Foundation,
located right here in the Bay Area.
It will consist of, you know,
seminars, expert round tables, site visits, right?
There's just no replacement, right,
for being in a place for meeting the people
behind the technology, right,
for marveling at the, you know,
intricacies of these
huge machines and infrastructure, right?
As a response to the demand
that we were hearing from our legislative partners
that with, you know,
32 out of the top 50 AI companies in the world
are located here in California, right?
It is a huge,
(audience applauds)
a huge responsibility that our legislators, right,
have taken on through their roles
in addition to, right,
the turnover of over 50% of legislators
within the last two and a half years,
because of a term limit ballot initiative expiring.
So we have our work cut out for us,
but to be that kind of foundation of, right,
the representatives of the facts
and of the research world
through our 12 institutional partners,
including the community colleges,
we're really thrilled
to be able to represent that
in addition to the more full context
of the other stakeholders
that are constantly in the hallways of our state capital.
And I have to say there are other models
of legislative training academies.
There's a particular organization called Capital Impact,
which has been providing programming for years.
And the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation among others
public funded an analysis
of what made that legislative training program effective.
And according to the participants,
it was having the community perspective represented.
So much more fully
than these communities are able to represent themselves
in the halls of state capitals.
To counterbalance the other stakeholders.
So we are,
we've committed to two years of this legislative academy
and would love your thoughts, right,
on what you are seeing right from the AI world
with the policy aspect
that you would suggest our incorporation.
So, thank you.
- Fantastic.
And I love that you mentioned community,
community engagement.
I know in the governor's state of the state address,
just this week he gave a shout out
to the Jobs First initiative.
Stewart I wanted to give you an opportunity
to share a little bit on what's the trajectory ahead
and kudos for getting more than 10,000 experts
and community members
as part of the process for that initiative.
- Yeah, I appreciate that.
Yeah, the governor is very proud of this,
which is great since Abby and I
spent a long weekends actually writing that legislation
back in 2021.
So Jobs First was also initiative
kind of breaking down barriers and silos
within the state government.
The original initiative was three state agencies,
GO-Biz, Labor Agency and OPR.
Collectively, $600 million goes out to 13 regions
throughout the state of California.
Whittled back to about $450 million two years ago
when we kind of hit a little bit of a budget crunch.
But generally the governor talks about Jobs First
is really the blueprint for the demand side.
And so how do we really talk to business
and learn what the demand is gonna be for the future
and really start to understand
an economic development role within this,
but also with the workforce development lens.
Second part to that,
he calls it the three-legged stool,
is there master plan and career education,
which we launched a few weeks thereafter.
And that was started with the K-16 collaborative dollars,
which also utilized the same 13 regions.
And so collectively with that three legged stool,
we've invested over $750 million
within these 13 regions around education.
So on the education side,
obviously we call that the supply side.
And so really blending demand and supply together
and really thinking about what career pathways
are gonna look like from the demand side.
And so these heavy investments
is the first time in the state of California
we've done this.
And so for us it's just a great opportunity
for the next administration with us waning at 15,
15-ish months left,
to really take a hold of that.
We will obviously continue
through the end of the administration
with this initiative,
with a heavy focus on what are the next steps.
Obviously we see a key role for the community colleges,
our CSUs and our UC systems
to really start to listen to the demand side and how,
AI is a great example of how fast things are gonna change
and are changing.
And so with the MOUs
that we're signing with the governor
recently here in San Francisco
and previously with NVIDIA,
that is, that just shows how much he's into
the business side of it.
And so I think our opportunities
with the community colleges
and workforce is really figuring out
how we get the supply side to really work well.
- Fantastic.
So I think we've heard loud and clear this morning
that it's about both the technology and the people,
the thoughtful and ambitious leaders
who are centering students and humans in all of this work.
And so I just want to thank everyone here
who's seated for what you're doing every day.
It matters.
I know it's been a very challenging year,
has it been only a year since we last convened?
We have some wisdom highlights from the last year.
But thank you for what you're doing
and please join me in sharing applause
for our wonderful panelist.
(audience applauds)
(indistinct chatter)
- All right, if you are exiting,
I hope you're walking to our booth
where we're giving free AI consulting services
to a hundred institutions across the United States.
But if you're not exiting for that,
I hope you stay for the next four minutes.
So I can actually explain why that's important
and what we here at DataKind do with you and for you.
So hi everyone, I'm Caitlin Augustin.
I'm the Vice President of Product and Programs at DataKind.
DataKind is a global non-profit organization
focused on using data and AI for social impact.
We've heard a couple of great panels
and conversations this morning about AI and innovation
and how that is so necessary
for making the impact we hope to have
on students across the United States.
Now here, DataKind,
we believe that AI solutions are not just technical.
They are co-created with institutions and they must be,
they must be transparent,
inclusive, and co-created.
And when we build solutions like that,
we believe that they have a huge impact.
And we are offering those services
thanks to a generous philanthropic brand
to work with a hundred institutions
across the United States.
And we're hoping a number of you here in California
to build out solutions that have an impact
on your communities.
Now what does that mean?
So when data kind worked with a mid-size MSI
in an urban setting,
a couple of years ago
on their challenges around graduation,
we helped them increase their graduation rate by 32%.
Now that wasn't magic,
that was identifying the specific problem they had
and not providing a generalized one model fits all solution.
In their case, they started to realize
that students who were seniors
were exiting without a degree,
but all of their student support mechanisms
were for undergraduates.
So we helped them build a model
that would identify those students
who were at risk of not graduating
and identify what was causing that risk.
What was the reason they were at risk of not graduating
and surface that information to their advising team.
So rather than their advisors looking through
sort of a needle in a haystack
to figure out which student they should support
at what time they,
we were able to use that information
and make direct connections
in a timely way with students
to get them the support they needed then.
Now that type of approach relies on transparency.
It relies on this co-created approach
of understanding what does an institution
need at this particular time?
What insights do they need
in order to build trust in that AI solution?
And how will they implement it?
How can this solution exist long-term
and be sustainable and part of their existing workflows?
And with DataKind, we do this,
we partner with institutions
for years at a time to build out these solutions
in a way that makes sense for you.
Now, I think I wet your appetite,
'cause the room got a lot quieter
once I said free AI and co-creation.
So I want, I want to emphasize that.
So we've had a lot of success
building predictive analytics
with institutions and alongside institutions.
And our bias is that these solutions
should be accessible to everyone,
not just institutions who can pay,
not just institutions who have partnerships
with large tech entities.
Every institution should have these tools
to be able to make an impact.
And as we go beyond just predictive analytics,
we are also looking for partnerships
on other parts of the AI sphere,
because we believe it can be additive
for impact in places like building up your data trust.
Yes, predictive analytics is great,
but if you don't trust the data
that is behind those analytics,
you will never actually use those predictive models.
AI tools can help with the data quality assessments,
it can help build the connections between data sets
to be sure that you have the right data out
and it can be used to make sense of the information
that you have in your system.
Yes, predictive analytics are great.
Where we're going now from that story I just told
about being able to predict the students
at risk of non graduation
and give the intervention
is actually to take that step further,
to say what is the next action
that a counselor should take with these students?
So we're not just saying, here's the information,
but here's how you use that information.
Well, we're also in kind of an interesting conversation
that I think many of you are in
of how messy transcripts are, right?
Those transcript documents,
sometimes they're still just PDFs,
sometimes they have a ton of free texts
that you're trying to interpret.
We've been working with a number of partners
across the US, including here in California,
to make sense of transcripts
and to figure out students
who have earned all the credits for a degree,
how do we give them a degree easily?
So these are a couple of areas
that we think are really promising for AI.
And again, we're looking for partners
to grow and to build the impact there.
I think I'm just about at my five minutes.
So again, I'm Caitlin Augustin, I'm from DataKind.
We build and co-create AI solutions for social impact.
We are supported to do this work at no cost to institutions,
thanks to philanthropy,
'cause our work is only impactful if it is useful to you.
So please come by our booth and talk to us about this work.
(audience applauds)
- Okay, we've got one last activity for you.
You do not want to miss this piece.
We have pushed back the panel, breakout start sessions,
so don't feel like you have to rush out
to get to your breakout sessions,
but you absolutely do not want to miss this part.
So we're thrilled to prevent AI,
to present AI, Friend or Foe.
So I'd like to invite Greg Langner
to come out and introduce
what will be our student skit.
(audience applauds)
- Thank you all for dedicating some of your attention
this morning to our faculty student collaboration,
AI Friend or Foe.
I'm Dr. Greg Langner,
professor of communication and media studies
at Antelope Valley College
in the far north rural region of Los Angeles County,
where thanks to my colleague,
Dr. Norma Jones and the concerted efforts of faculty,
we have been at the forefront of equipping the academy
for a future of higher education,
enriched but invariably impacted by artificial intelligence.
And a group of theater students
lose their set design just before a class deadline.
Tensions rise with time ticking and no backup plan,
they take a big risk by turning to AI.
Witness a surprising mix of chaos,
creativity and collaboration.
Challenging assumptions about teamwork and technology.
So that's the official description.
But here's what I'd like to add in short,
this short
one act sketch
illustrates students' relatively realistic use of AI
in real time relevance.
In using AI to help us both structure
and study our own collaboration process.
We encounter at every stage very real
(dramatic chord plays)
cinematic,
(audience laughs)
very real, ethical and artistic tensions,
which were in fact crucial for us to accept
as part of the process.
In the context of college,
where we ask students to aspire
to their own higher learning,
we can ethically and effectively
use such a profoundly disruptive tool
to the extent
we are willing to question and challenge ourselves first.
(audience member sneezes)
Bless you.
One hallmark of critical thinking.
(audience laughs)
One hallmark of critical thinking
is one's willingness to reason
beyond the familiar and comfortable,
where and when appropriate for new technology to step in.
We all have an opportune responsibility
to expand our thinking,
to find more room to grow
as a learning community
and to get to ask of and witness
more potential and greatness
from the students
whose learning we aspire to serve together.
Friends and colleagues, AI, Friend or Foe.
(audience applauds)
- Okay, everyone,
you've been working on this all semester.
So everyone take a minute
to revise and finalize your set designs
before you start building.
And don't forget,
a photo of your final set build
will be due tonight on Canvas at 11:59.
If you have any questions,
be sure to check the syllabus
for assignment details
or let me know if you need any help.
- Thank you. - Thank you.
- Thanks.
- Okay.
- All right guys.
Set building day.
- Hey.
- Taylor, can you pull up our design?
Let's see what we got.
- Yeah, I finished 'em last night.
They're on my laptop.
Lemme get them.
Um.
Oh, fuck.
(audience laughs)
My computer won't turn on.
- What?
Let me try.
(audience laughs)
Well, can't you just get it from your phone?
- Yeah, no, it's only on my laptop.
- You mean to tell me in 2025 you're not on cloud?
- Guys, our set designs are due tonight
and no one has a design you worked on?
- What about maybe we try and draw something up from memory?
- How much do you remember?
- Not much.
(audience laughs)
Or
maybe we can use AI
to help us out?
- It's just going to spit out some generic design
or something confusing and weird.
And then we'll be at square one again.
- Not the (speaks foreign language),
the assignment isn't about (speaks foreign language),
the objective is to build set pieces based off of
the script we chose.
- Let's,
let's just see what it gives us.
Try out some prompts.
Grand Castle.
Space Disco, right,
neon lights.
- Boom.
(audience laughs)
- Alex, please pull up the script.
Jordan, stop wasting time.
This isn't some Interstellar Mama Mia show.
Focus.
- Guys, I don't think we should do this.
I really can't get in trouble for cheating.
I graduate this semester.
- Well, is it really cheating?
I mean, what's the policy on using AI?
- Huh?
- The what, politics?
(audience laughs)
Why are we worried about politics?
This isn't political science.
- The policy.
- Policy, right, I knew that.
- Yeah.
- That's a good question.
I don't know.
Let's ask.
Hey professor,
what's our class AI policy?
- It's in the syllabus.
(audience laughs)
- Backpack maybe, I dunno.
- I got it (indistinct).
(audience laughs)
- Brainstorming.
- Yeah.
We used to use AI, brainstorming.
Oh,
you cannot use AI generated content
as a replacement for appropriate research.
- Great.
The assignment is to actually build the set.
So AI isn't doing the work for us.
We're good.
It's a tool that's helping us.
- Well, if the syllabus says it's okay.
Cozy.
- Dramatic
- Vintage set design.
- With warm colors
and antique props.
- A cozy, dramatic vintage set design with warm colors
Oh.
That's actually pretty close to what I had in mind.
Oh, and look, it suggests a deep red
as part of the color scheme.
Alex, does that work (speaks foreign language)?
- Yeah, that works.
- Can we add like an arch right here?
- If we do, it'll need extra support.
Maybe we can ask for some suggestions
on how to make it more stable.
- It says reinforcing the base
can help prevent the arch from breaking.
- And look, we've combined creativity and structure.
It actually looks like a set.
(computer beeps indistinctly)
- What about adding a giant inflatable unicorn?
(audience laughs)
- Okay.
Well, not everything it does is genius, obviously.
- But it's, at least it has a sense of humor.
- Look at that.
You successfully reimagined your set design as a group
with AI as your learning tools.
- Yeah, turns out AI can be a helpful resource after all.
- I guess it's not as bad as I thought.
- It's a lot like any other tools.
Teamwork and tools, not too shabby.
- We're done.
- Well, y'all still need to actually build your set.
- The assignment.
- Right - Right.
- Okay. - Right.
- Okay, (speaks foreign language)
- Right, let's get to work.
(audience applauds)
(audience applause continues)
- Hi, how's everyone doing?
(audience cheers)
Can we give our students just one more round of applause?
(audience applauds and cheers)
So our students showed us.
So let me introduce our faculty, our students,
our faculty directors.
First of all, Sarah (indistinct).
(audience applauds)
Serena (indistinct).
David Holmes.
(audience applauds)
Paulina Vierra.
And Brian Solano.
(audience applauds)
May I bring on our faculty directors?
Alright, come on out,
Carla Verona.
(audience applauds and cheers)
And Dr. Greg Langner.
(audience applauds)
So our students in the skit,
our students showed us how AI
can be a helpful tool when used the right way.
First objective is, okay, it's in the syllabus, right?
And then they used it to ethically help guide their build.
Interestingly, when we began the skit,
one of our faculty directors, sorry,
Carla was like,
I'm not so much loving this AI process, right?
But then she discovered how useful it can be
and now she's carrying that learning into the community.
Sorry,
as the president of the board of trustees
for the Antelope Valley Union High School District.
(audience applauds)
Together this team illustrates the powerful partnership
of all of our groups in college working together
and branching that growth into our broader community.
So, and also illustrating
what's possible when we are open-minded
to better serve our students.
Ooh, sorry, asthma.
So next, please allow me to say some thank yous.
Thank you for having us here.
Thank you to Don Daves-Rougeaux
for not only visiting AVC,
but inspiring us to push further our boundaries
and imagining what's possible.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
A huge thanks to the Chancellor's office.
Thank you for allowing this opportunity to share our work.
Thank you so much.
(audience applauds)
And thank you to the team here.
I've got Anthony, Catherine,
Charles, Jennifer, Travis, and so many others.
Thank you for helping us put together this performance,
supporting this performance as we came in here.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
At AVC, special thanks to our president,
Dr. Jennifer Zellet,
for empowering us to find new and creative ways
to better serve students.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
Also at Antelope Valley College,
special thanks to our Vice President
of Academic Affairs, Dr. Kathy Bakhit.
She came up with this idea.
Yeah.
(audience applauds)
It is through our leadership,
our executive leadership,
that they're creating this
wonderful collaborative environment
that allows us to learn and thrive together.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
Thank you to again,
our wonderful, wonderful faculty directors.
We, our equity advisor Monica Esquivel
couldn't join us,
to our wonderful students,
(audience applauds)
Sarah, Serina, David, Paulina,
thank you for your performance.
(audience cheers and applauds)
Let me end by saying, as a campus
we have heard the chancellor's call.
She said to us, I remember it.
At the online teaching conference.
Our time is now,
in one voice at Antelope Valley College.
We are ready.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
And now may I invite everyone to lunch?
Alright, let's go.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)
(indistinct chatter continues)